Finding Aid for Theodore H. Hubbell Papers 1833-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore H. Hubbell papers
1833-1988
1852-1970
Hubbell, Theodore H.
Professor of entomology at the University of Michigan. Personal and professional papers of Hubbell and his wife Grace Griffin Hubbell; also collected genealogical and family papers relating to the Hubbell and Hussey families (Grace Griffin Hubbell's mother was Lenora Hussey Griffin); Hussey family series includes papers of John Milton and Mary C. Hussey and their children and relate to John M. Hussey's Civil War service, Ohio agriculture and Grange activities and family life and customs; Hubbell family series includes papers of Clarence W. and Winifred Waters Hubbell relating in part to his work as engineer in the Philippines, 1907-1913; and collected Hubbell family photos and albums, including views of Benzonia, Michigan family farm and relating to C. W. Hubbell's service as engineer in the Philippine Islands, 1909-1911; also personal photograph series, including various residences of Hubbell, his scientific field trips to Tennessee, Florida, and the Philippines, and postcard views of Michigan communities.
90180 Aa 2
7.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 4509 ) was received in May 1990 from Roger Hubbell, executor of the Theodore H. Hubbell estate.
The collection is open for research.
Theodore Huntington Hubbell was professor of entomology at the University of Michigan from 1946 to 1968 and director of its Museum of Zoology from 1956 until his retirement in 1968. Even after his ostensible retirement, Hubbell came to the museum daily and served as "everybody's mentor" until his death in 1989. Hubbell's professional reputation rested on his enduring interest in and extensive writings on Orthoptera, and his local reputation rested on the organizational skills he demonstrated in the administration of space and resources within the museum. Theodore was born in Detroit in 1897 to Clarence (Detroit's Civil Engineer) and Winifred Hubbell. The family spent the years 1907 to 1913 in the Philippine Islands where Clarence worked as civil engineer for Manila and where Theodore first developed his interests in natural history and entomology. The younger Hubbell earned two degrees from the University of Michigan: his B.A. in 1920 and his Ph.D. in 1934, working in the interim as a professor of entomology in Gainesville at the University of Florida.
In one sense Hubbell never left Ann Arbor for, as he continued his doctoral research, he was building up the collection of Orthoptera in the Museum of Zoology. This continuing relationship was doubtless encouraged by Hubbell's mentor, Alexander Ruthven, and by the construction of a new museums building in which to house the burgeoning collections. While in Florida, Hubbell did not stray far from his Michigan roots intellectually as he joined a staff anchored by J. Speed Rogers, another student of Ruthven. Both men took to heart Ruthven's teaching that a systematic understanding of zoology, one that linked historical geography and habitats to the distribution and evolution of insects, was the most rational natural philosophy. This close relationship between environment and fauna was a hallmark of University of Michigan zoologists and may be seen as laying the groundwork for the ecological sciences. Both Rogers and Hubbell returned to the University of Michigan in 1946, Rogers as director of the Museum of Zoology, Hubbell as curator of insects at the museum and professor of entomology.
Rogers' and Hubbell's impact on the museum was immediate and beneficial as they reorganized the extensive holdings of the insects to make them more accessible to the appropriate researchers. They each brought their own considerable area of expertise to play on the museum's holdings of craneflies and grasshoppers. With the unexpected death of Rogers in 1955, Hubbell assumed more obvious control of the administrative aspects of the museum. Under his direction, existing programs of teaching and research were broadened, ties with the zoology department were strengthened, systematic biology came to prominence in the curriculum, and a research wing was added to the museum with monies from the National Science Foundation. Hubbell was instrumental in the formation of the inter-university Organization for Tropical Studies, played a significant role in expanding the study of biological systematics in a number of contexts, and advised the National Science Foundation on facilities and programs most needful to zoological museums. In recognition of his accomplishments and service the University conferred a distinguished faculty achievement award upon Hubbell.
Theodore Hubbell married Grace Griffin in Ann Arbor in June 1927. By so doing, Hubbell linked himself to a family with further ties to the University of Michigan. Grace's uncle, William J. Hussey, was professor of astronomy at the university in 1891-1892 and from 1915 until his death in 1926; William's wife, Ethel Fountain Hussey, was a distinguished alumna whose philanthropy is commemorated by an eponymous room in the Michigan League. Grace's cousin, Roland F. Hussey, taught Ornithology in 1918 and returned (at the behest of Theodore Hubbell) as visiting zoologist specializing in Hemiptera during the 1950s. Another cousin, Russell C. Hussey, was professor of geology during the 1920s and served as assistant to the dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts during the 1930s. Theodore and Grace had three children, Roger, Mary Joan, and Stephen.
The Theodore Huntington Hubbell papers form a disparate collection that documents not only his professional career as an entomologist and curator, but also sheds light on the late nineteenth and early twentieth-century Hubbell and Hussey families. The far-reaching scope of these papers derives from Theodore H. and Grace Griffin Hubbell's diligent collecting of family papers and photographs. The bulk of the early materials are Hussey family papers consisting of the personal papers of Grace's mother, Lenora Hussey Griffin, and her mother's nuclear family. This family consisted of Lenora's parents, John Milton and Mary C. Hussey, and her siblings, William J., Edgar P., Arthur, and Alice, and their spouses.
The Theodore H. Hubbell papers should be viewed as a subset of a larger universe of collections which include the Hussey family and Hubbell family collections here at the Bentley Historical Library and the John Milton Hussey letters and diary at the University of Michigan's William Clements Library. The strengths of this collection are diverse, ranging from a rich run of Civil War correspondence between John Milton and Mary C. Hussey, to Lenora Hussey Griffin's letters to her family about her education at Stanford, to Theodore Hubbell and J. Speed Rogers correspondence with various entomologists regarding field work and collecting. The collection will be of use to researchers interested in nineteenth-century agriculture, the Grange in Ohio, family life and customs, Joseph B. Steere's expedition to the Philippine Islands, and visual images of turn of the century Michigan and the University of Michigan. The collection is weak on documenting Theodore Hubbell's work as a teacher and curator of the Museum of Zoology; these records are retained by the museum for use in administering their collections.
The Theodore H. Hubbell papers span the years 1833-1988, with the bulk of materials covering the years 1852-1970; they are organized into five series: Genealogy, Hussey Family, Hubbell Family, Personal, and Professional. The first three series reflect Theodore and Grace Griffin Hubbell's efforts as genealogist/archivist for their respective families. The Personal series primarily deals with the private lives of Theodore and Grace Hubbell, but it also contains some materials linked to the first three series in the correspondence with Lenora Hussey Griffin. The materials in the first four series were rearranged during the course of processing to facilitate access to the Hussey and Hubbell family papers. The last series consists of Theodore Hubbell's professional correspondence (including letters to his cousin Roland F. Hussey) and project related materials; this series retains its original order.
Subjects:
Agriculture--United States.; Entomology.; Hubbell, Theodore Huntington, 1897-1989.; Hubbell family.; Hussey family.; Ohio.; Ohio--Social life and customs.; National Grange.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Zoology.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Albums.; Benzonia (Mich.); Beulah (Mich.); Dwellings.; Fort Sill (Okla.); Frankfort (Mich.); Hubbell, Theodore Huntington, 1897-1989.; Milford (Mich.); University Museums Building (University of Michigan); Philippines--History--1898-1946.; University Hall (University of Michigan); World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Hubbell, Clarence, 1870-1950.; Hubbell, Grace Griffin.; Hubbell, Winifred.; Hussey, John Milton.; Hussey, Mary C.; Hussey, Roland F.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; Rogers, J. Speed (James Speed), 1892-1955; Steere, Joseph Beal, 1842-1940.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Postcards.
- Genealogy, 1880s-1978
  The Genealogy (1880s-1978) series consists of fourteen folders arranged by the family to which they refer. These materials have been collected by at least three persons, William J. Hussey, Lenora Hussey Griffin, and Grace Griffin Hubbell, so there is some overlap in the notes on and description of the various families. The documentation of the Hussey and Hubbell families is especially detailed for the mid-nineteenth century; this is largely a by-product of the amount of primary source materials kept by the families.
  - Hubbell family, 1970-1980s
    - "The Hubbell family in America" (Box 1)
    - Forebears/other families (Box 1)
    - Family tree (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1978 (Box 1)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hussey family, 1880s-1964
    - "A branch of the Hussey family in America,", 1964 (Box 1)
    - Hannah Ann Hussey biography, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
    - Notes (by William J. Hussey), 1910-1925 (Box 1)
    - Notes/Correspondence, 1880s-1950s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Severn family, 1960s-1970s
    - Notes (by Lenora H. Griffin), 1960s (Box 1)
    - Notes (by Grace G. Hubbell), 1970s (Box 1)
- Hussey Family (), 1833-1965; primarily 1852-1930
  The Hussey Family (1833-1965) series, which runs eighteen linear inches, is arranged according to the familial generation of creation for the materials and mainly consists of correspondence and financial materials. The John Milton and Mary C. Hussey subseries is arranged alphabetically according to type of material. This subseries is the result of substantial rearrangement of the materials. The letters between John Milton and Mary C. Hussey reveal much about his confidence in her ability to manage the farm while he was in the service during the Civil War. The originals of John's correspondence are held by the Clements Library. Their correspondence with their children illuminates a typical late nineteenth-century occupational mobility pattern as the children leave the landed gentry for professional positions.
  The family life and customs of this particular family are further revealed in the Children of John M. and Mary C. Hubbell subseries. This subseries has also been altered in the course of processing and is now arranged alphabetically by name of child. The bulk of materials in this subseries was created by Lenora Hussey Griffin; that more of her papers remain extant is likely due to her remarkable longevity and to the fact that her daughter, Grace Griffin Hubbell, carefully saved them. There are also William J. Hussey materials in this subseries; these should be viewed as complementary to the Hussey Family collection housed at the Bentley Library.
  - William Hussey
    - Student notebooks, 1819 (Box 1)
  - John Milton and Mary C. Hussey, 1833-1947
    - Correspondence (with each other), 1852-1891
      - 1852-1853 (Box 1)
        Originals and typescripts
      - John to Mary, 1864 (Box 1)
        originals and typescripts
      - Mary to John, 1864 (Box 1)
      - 1891 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (extended family), 1847-1917; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Children, 1875-1918
      - Alice Hussey (Rose), 1884-1894 (Box 1)
      - Arthur W. (and Lillian) Hussey, 1875-1914; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Edgar P. (and Flora) Hussey, 1875-1893; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1889-1917; 2 folders (Box 1)
        (includes Stanford letters)
      - William J. (and Ethel F. and Mary R.) Hussey, 1880-1918; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial/Legal, 1833-1947
      - Account books, 1853-1913
        - Farm accounts, 1853-1876 (Box 1)
        - Threshing (and miscellaneous), 1857-1858 (Box 1)
        - Household, 1903-1913 (Box 1)
          (includes genealogy)
      - Correspondence and advertising, 1855-1893 (Box 1)
      - Hussey farm, 1833-1947
        - Architect's plan, circa 1860 (Box 2)
        - Deeds, 1833-1936; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Estate (J.M. Hussey) appraisal, 1914-1915 (Box 2)
        - Estate auction, circa 1947 (Box 2)
      - Grange materials, 1861-1880s
        - Mercer Co. (OH), 1861-1880s (Box 2)
          (includes The Scythe, 1877)
        - Account books (Mercer Co.), 1872-1876 (Box 2)
        - Constitutions (Hocking and Hancock, OH), 1870s (Box 2)
        - Articles of Incorporation (St. Mary's, OH), 1875 (Box 2)
      - Justice of the Peace (J.M. Hussey), 1865-1872
        - Articles of Agreement, 1865-1872 (Box 2)
        - Estate Executor, 1865-1870
          - John Parrot, 1865 (Box 2)
          - William Hussey, 1865; 2 folders (Box 2)
          - David Holmes, 1868-1869 (Box 2)
          - Miscellaneous, 1865-1870 (Box 2)
        - Marriage Licenses, 1868-1869 (Box 2)
      - Receipts, 1845-1880 (Box 2)
      - Tax receipts, 1851-1908; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Mary C. Hussey
        - Widow's pension, 1914 (Box 2)
        - Will, 1918 (Box 2)
    - Personal, 1847-1890s
      - Civil War materials (regimental listing, itinerary, memos, discharge), 1864 (Box 2)
      - Diaries, 1847-1863; 5 folders (Box 2)
        originals with partial typescript
      - Franklin Literary and Theological Society (Mendon, OH) minutes, 1867-1868 (Box 2)
      - New Light Christian Church, 1866 (Box 2)
      - Poetry/Reflections (some typescripts), 1853-1870 (Box 2)
      - Recipes, circa 1860s (Box 2)
      - Teaching notes, 1851-1862 (Box 2)
      - Temperance, 1859-1869
        - Broad Oak Resolution, 1859 (Box 2)
        - Union Township (Mercer Co.) Pledge, 1869 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1853-1890s (Box 2)
  - John Milton and Mary C. Hussey's Children, 1875-1965
    - Alice Hussey (Rose), 1878-1906
      - Correspondence, 1878-1906 (Box 2)
        (includes description of her fatal illness, 1906)
      - Correspondence to Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1884-1903 (Box 2)
    - Arthur W. (and Lillian) Hussey, 1877-1947
      - Correspondence to Edgar P. Hussey, 1877-1888 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1906-1947 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to William J. Hussey, 1906; 1918 (Box 2)
    - Edgar P. (and Flora) Hussey, 1875-1940
      - Correspondence, 1875-1886 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1926-1940 (Box 2)
    - Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1879-1965
      - Correspondence, 1912-1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence from George Griffin, 1909-1918 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with Jane Griffin, 1917-1947 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with Mary Griffin (Newton), 1916-1928 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Arthur W. Hussey, 1879 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to William J. Hussey, 1895-1896 (Box 2)
      - Diary, 1938-1961 (Box 2)
        (includes Grace Griffin Hubbell diary, 1956-1961)
      - Financial, 1892-1946
        - Deeds to West St. property, 1892-1897 (Box 2)
        - Ledger of receipts, 1935-1946 (Box 2)
      - Lesson books, undated; circa 1895 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous writings, 1890s (Box 2)
    - William J. Hussey, 1883-1931
      - Correspondence to Alice Hussey (Rose), 1883-1889 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Arthur W. Hussey, 1893; 1914 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Edgar P. Hussey, 1912-1913 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Ethel Fountain Hussey, 1912 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to Lenora Hussey (Griffin), 1895-1928 (Box 2)
      - Financial, 1919-1931
        - Estate of William J. Hussey, 1919-1931 (Box 2)
      - Personal (including biography, photograph and UM Oracle, 1893), 1893-1926 (Box 2)
      - Teaching, 1884-1885 (Box 2)
- Hubbell Family, 1860s-1964
  Theodore Hubbell likewise took pains to preserve the materials in the Hubbell Family (1860s-1964) series. This series runs eight linear inches and consists primarily of the papers of Clarence W. and Winifred Waters Hubbell and family photographs. These materials should also be used in conjunction with another Bentley Library collection, the Hubbell Family papers, with which there is considerable overlap. The strengths of this series reside in its documentation of Winifred Hubbell's writings and the photographs. The albums of family photographs will be of special interest to genealogists and researchers doing family history. During processing some photographs were removed from their physical proximity with this series and placed in the Personal series as it appeared that Theodore Hubbell created or collected those images.
  - Martha A.H. Bliss
    - Notebook (transcriptions), undated (Box 3)
  - Clarence W. Hubbell, 1900-1955
    - Correspondence (and death certificate, 1955), 1911-1914 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Winifred W. Hubbell, 1912-1914; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Financial (with Winifred W. Hubbell)
      - Account book, 1900-1906 (Box 3)
    - Writings, circa 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - Winifred W. Hubbell, circa 1910s-1950
    - Poetry/prose, 1910s-1940s; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Reminiscence ("Our Adventure in the Philippines"), circa 1950 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous poetry (Mildred Hubbell and F.B. Waters), undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1860s-1964
    - Album (Waters, Bliss, Hubbell), 1860s-1870s (Box 3)
    - Album (Hubbell?), circa 1920s (Box 3)
    - Hubbell family (Clarence, John S., and Roger), 1893-1910s (Box 3)
    - Theodore H. Hubbell, 1898-1920s (Box 3)
      (includes photograph of UM Les Voyageurs, 1917)
    - Grace Griffin Hubbell (Box 3)
    - Griffin-Hussey families (Box 3)
    - Winifred W. Hubbell, circa 1950 (Box 3)
    - Waters family, circa 1890s (Box 3)
    - Willard O. Waters, 1880s-1955 (Box 3)
    - Various families (Case, Huntington, Newcomb), circa 1890-1964 (Box 3)
    - Benzonia (MI) farm views, 1880s-1942 (Box 3)
    - Philippine Islands (C.W. Hubbell), 1909-1911 (Box 3)
- Personal, 1907-1988
  The Personal (1907-1988) series comprises sixteen linear inches of materials and is closely linked to the first three series; it is arranged alphabetically by type of material and consists of correspondence, Grace Griffin Hubbell materials, photographs, and other visual materials. As with the previous series, these materials have been moved in the course of processing, so researchers should avail themselves of cross-references in the folder listing. Grace Griffin Hubbell's correspondence with her mother, Lenora Hussey Griffin, is quite frank and reveals two fine intellects. Grace's reminiscences and notes on her chemotherapy after her cancer diagnosis are compelling.
  - Correspondence (general), 1967-1988; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (topical), 1907-1983
    - Clements Library (re Hussey books), 1971 (Box 3)
    - Griffin family (excluding Lenora Hussey Griffin), 1907-1973 (Box 3)
    - Hussey family, 1927-1983 (Box 3)
    - Re Military Service, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Trip around the world, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Trip to Burma and China, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Grace Griffin Hubbell, 1916-1982
    - Correspondence with Lenora Hussey Griffin, 1916-1970; 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Diary (fragment), 1925-1926 (Box 4)
    - Publications, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Record of Chemotherapy, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Thoughts and mementos, 1981 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes family photographs of the Hubbell and related families, the Hubbell farm and residences in Ann Arbor, a glass lantern slide of University Hall and turn of the century postcards of the University of Michigan, Beulah and Benzonia, Michigan, and World War I images of Fort Sill, Oklahoma.
  - Photographs, 1919-1971
    - Homes/Dwellings, 1920s-1971
      - Pi Beta Phi House, circa 1927 (Box 4)
      - Hussey farm (Mendon, OH), 1920s-1930s (Box 4)
      - Hubbell farm/Hillhollow (Milford, MI), 1930s-1948 (Box 4)
      - Hibiscus Park (Gainesville, FL), 1928-1929 (Box 4)
      - Cochlough Hill (Gainesville, FL), 1940-1946 (Box 4)
      - Bishop house/2505 Geddes (Ann Arbor, MI), 1948-1950s (Box 4)
        (includes canoeing on Huron)
      - 940 Rock Creek Drive (Ann Arbor, MI), undated; 1971 (Box 4)
    - Trips, 1919-1960
      - Field Work (TN and FL), 1919-1927 (Box 4)
      - Philippine Islands, 1945; 1960 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Museums Building construction, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Lantern Slide of University Hall (UM), 1880s (Box 4)
    - Negatives of Hubbell family, 1930s-1970 (Box 4)
  - Post Cards, circa 1890s-1940s
    - Ann Arbor, MI (UM), 1890s-1940s (Box 4)
    - Benzonia, MI, 1890s-1920 (Box 4)
    - Beulah, MI, 1890s-1920 (Box 4)
    - Frankfort, MI, 1890s-1939 (Box 4)
    - Michigan (general), 1900-1915 (Box 4)
    - Fort Sill, OK (WW I training), 1918 (Box 4)
- Professional (primarily 1930s-1960s), 1890-1988
  The Professional series (1890-1988, primarily 1930s-1960s) makes up the last half of the collection and runs four and one-third linear feet. The bulk of this series consists of correspondence which runs to more than three linear feet and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Also included in the series are Hubbell's vitae and letters of appointment and Hubbell's efforts to establish the field of biological systematics and other professional writing.
  - Vitae and letters of appointment
    - 1916-1960s (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1988
    The Correspondence subseries includes materials of Hubbell, J. Speed Rogers, and Alexander G. Ruthven as they managed the University of Michigan Museum of Zoology. It naturally includes letters from prominent University of Michigan zoologists, Cantrall, Dice, Gaige, Hussey, and Van Tyne, but it also contains correspondence with amateur entomologists who collected for the museum. Further correspondence of this type evidently has been retained by the Museum of Zoology to facilitate control over their collections. Among the materials in this subseries, the following are of special note: the letters with Roland F. Hussey which are both professional and intimately personal in nature; the J. Speed Rogers materials which detail the concurrent development of his and Hubbell's careers; and the correspondence regarding the Joseph B. Steere expeditions reflects Hubbell's profound interest in nailing down the details of Steere's itinerary.
    - A, 1955-1988 (Box 4)
    - Allee, W.C., 1950-1953 (Box 4)
    - Association for Tropical Biology, 1964-1966 (Box 4)
    - B, 1919-1981 (Box 4)
    - Bates, Marston, 1940-1974 (Box 4)
    - Bellamy, Ralph, 1938-1958 (Box 4)
    - Berner, Lewis, 1941-1961 (Box 4)
    - Brodknob, Pierce, 1947-1978 (Box 4)
    - Brown, Patricia (re Helen Gaige), 1986 (Box 4)
    - Burt, William H., 1946-1983 (Box 4)
    - Byers, George W., 1948-1967 (Box 4)
    - C, 1922-1976 (Box 4)